Finding Aid for the Paul B. MacCready Papers, 1931-2002 MacCreadyPB
California Institute of Technology Archives and Special Collections
- Audio-Visual Material, 7
  - Videos and Audio, 3
    - Paul B. MacCready: Unleashing Creativity While Still Getting the Job Done. Keynote from OOPSLA 98. The 13th Annual ACM Sigplan Conference on Object Oriented Programming Systems, Languages, and Applications (Vancouver, BC), 1998 October 20 - 22; MacCreadyPB_07_03_019_12; VHS. Color. 1 hour (Box
      Created by University Video Communications. Lecture. Features slides and clips from various films about MacCready's projects.
    - 1999 SSA Convention (sponsored by Smoky Mountain Soaring Association). Part I Exhibit Hall slideshow (23 min) and Part II SSA Banquet with Keynote speaker Paul MacCready, MacCreadyPB_07_03_020_01; VHS. Color. 2 hours (Box 7.20, Folder 1)
      Created by Heads Up Aerial Advertising and Smoky Mountain Soaring Association. Opens with a commercial from Heads Up Aerial Advertising then ~ 20 minutes of slideshow, followed by footage of banquet.
    - MMETS (Materials and Manufacturing & Enabling Technologies Series) lecture: Paul MacCready, 1999; MacCreadyPB_07_03_020_02; VHS. Color. 1 hour (Box 7.20, Folder 2)
    - CBS News clip on the Institute for Educational Advancement, 2000; MacCreadyPB_07_03_020_03; VHS. 5 min. 22 sec. (Box 7.20, Folder 3)
      John Blackstone piece on the Institute for Educational Advancement founded by Paul MacCready. Includes brief background of MacCready's works. THE IEA is a workshop for gifted children. Introduced by Bob Schiffer.
    - "Pioneers of Flight" AeroVironment's Revolutionary Air Vehicles 1977 - 2000. Discover Magazine, 2000 February 27; MacCreadyPB_07_03_020_04; VHS. Color. 25 min. (Box 7.20, Folder 4)
      Created by Discover Magazine/ Discovery Channel Big Rock Productions Producer, writer director: Julie Mirocha, Pinball Productions. Features some of the various AeroVironment projects that were developed, including Gossamer Condor, Gossamer Albatross, Helios.
    - Institute for Educational Advancement (Kids Model airplane workshop), 2000 July; MacCreadyPB_07_03_020_05; VHS. Color. 41 min. 25 sec. (Box 7.20, Folder 5)
      Paul MacCready's personal footage of kids' (mostly 16 yr olds) model sailplane workshop in office. Flying on soccer field, in school gym (Luther Burbank High School).
    - SHA (Sailplane Homebuilders Association?), 2000 September; MacCreadyPB_07_03_020_06; VHS. Color. 2 hours (Box 7.20, Folder 6)
      Personal footage of presentations at the SHA meeting featuring Paul MacCready, Tyler MacCready, et al.
    - Scientific American Frontiers Episode 1109 "Flying Free", 2001 April 10; MacCreadyPB_07_03_020_07; .MOV. Color. 56 min. 46 sec. (Box 7.20, Folder 7)
      Created by Chedd-Angier Productions for Scientific American.
    - Pool Fluid Mechanics, 2001 August 29; MacCreadyPB_07_03_020_08; VHS. Color. 5 min. 56 sec. (Box 7.20, Folder 8)
      Personal footage of testing wakes/vortices in pool. Paul MacCready is operating the camera and narrating. Tyler MacCready is helping.
    - Vortex brief, 2001 October 3; MacCreadyPB_07_03_020_09; VHS. Color. 3 min. (Box 7.20, Folder 9)
      Pesonal footage of Paul and family experimenting with vortices in the pool.
    - Clips used in MacCready lecture, 2001 November 11; MacCreadyPB_07_03_020_10; VHS. Color. 30 min. (Box 7.20, Folder 10)
      Collection of video clips used for a lecture. Duplicate footage of material used in other videos.
    - Paul MacCready, Aerospace Discover Awards 2002, MacCreadyPB_07_03_020_11; VHS. Color. 5 min. (Box 7.20, Folder 11)
      Created by Discover Magazine. Footage of MacCready's various projects including clips of the Gossamer Condor and Gassamer Albatross short films.
    - Hi-8 Tapes Miscellaneous
    - Jack Lambie interviews Peter Riedel (German gliding champion) tape 1 of 3, 1995 October; MacCreadyPB_07_03_021_01; Hi-8. Color. 1 hour 8 min. (approx) (Box 7.21, Folder 1)
      Unedited personal video of interview. Wife of Riedel and cameraman are often talking in the background.
    - Jack Lambie interviews Peter Riedel tape 2 of 3/ Misc. Lambie, 1995 October; MacCreadyPB_07_03_021_02; Hi-8. Color. 1 hour 15 min. (approx) (Box 7.21, Folder 2)
      1. Riedel talks of his experiences in Nazi Germany. 2. Footage of Jack Lambie and other in quarry, miscellaneous footage of Lambie's sculptures.
    - Copper State EAA (Experimental Aircraft Association)/ More Jack Lambie interviewing Peter Riedel tape 3 of 3, 1995 October; MacCreadyPB_07_03_021_03; Hi-8. Color. 2 hours (Box 7.21, Folder 3)
      1. Airplane/glider convention. 2. Jack Lambie interviewing Peter Riedel. Tape is blank for several minutes between segments.
    - Saturn dealership event, 1996; MacCreadyPB_07_03_021_04; Hi-8. Color. 1 hour (approx) (Box 7.21, Folder 4)
      1. At Monrovia Saturn dealership event with AeroVironment. 2. Toy electric car races followed by Paul MacCready talk on the future of electric vehicles and efficiency. 3. Flying test 4. Ralph Ray's shop testing stationary bike contraption. 5. Paul MacCready experimenting with pool vortices. 6. Bike race. 7. Windmill farm.
    - Tests, LF?, Presentation of Lindbergh Award to Sylvia Earle (part 1 of 2), 1996 May 21; MacCreadyPB_07_03_021_05; Hi-8 (Box 7.21, Folder 5)
      Tape has several short segments. 1. Paul and Judy MacCready talking in a bedroom (app. 1 minute). 2. Discussion of display of Gossamer Condor at the National Air & Space Museum (?). 3. Lindbergh Foundation 1996 awards ceremony (pre-event, Sylvia Earle presentation). Paul MacCready is featured briefly introducing Reeve Lindbergh.
    - Presentation of Lindbergh Award to Sylvia Earle (part 2 of 2), 1996 May 21; MacCreadyPB_07_03_021_06; Hi-8. Color. 46 min. 45 sec. (Box 7.21, Folder 6)
      Recording of 1996 Lindbergh awards with Sylvia Earle. Paul MacCready introduces. Continuation of Earle presentation followed by post-event dinner.
    - Untitled [prototype testing], 1997 May/1997 August 22/1998 February; MacCreadyPB_07_03_021_07; Hi-8. Color. 15 min. (approx) (Box 7.21, Folder 7)
      1. Brief footage of friends of MacCready chatting. 2. Paul MacCready filming the pool at night. 3.Testing UAV in gym.
    - 20th Anniversary party for Gossamer Condor/Black Sheep Squadron/IHPVA, 1997 August 23; other dates 1997; MacCreadyPB_07_03_021_08; Hi-8. Color. 3 hours (approx) (Box 7.21, Folder 8)
      1. Personal video of Gossamer Condor party at the house of Sam Duran in Bakersfield, CA. Paul MacCready is operating the camera and narrating. 2. Presentations from an International Human Powered Vehicle Association meeting.
    - 22nd International Birdman Rally, Japan, 1998; MacCreadyPB_07_03_021_09; Hi-8. Color. 30 min. (approx) (Box 7.21, Folder 9)
      Program taped off TV. People (college-aged) compete in human powered flight vehicles that are similar to Gossamer Condor.
    - Tests of model planes, 1998; MacCreadyPB_07_03_021_10; Hi-8. Color. 1 hour (approx) (Box 7.21, Folder 10)
      Paul, Judy and Tyler MacCready testing UAV.
    - IHPVA meeting and slideshow, 1998 January 17; MacCreadyPB_07_03_021_11; Hi-8. Color. 10 min. (approx) (Box 7.21, Folder 11)
    - Christmas 98, 1998 November; MacCreadyPB_07_03_021_12; Hi-8. Color. 20 min. (approx) (Box 7.21, Folder 12)
      1. Paul MacCready testing camera in his house (10 seconds). 2. AeroVironment presentation to students (about 2 minutes). 3. Christmas party.
    - Miscellaneous, 1999 December - 2000 January; MacCreadyPB_07_03_021_13; Hi-8. Color. 45 min. (approx) (Box 7.21, Folder 13)
      1. Paul MacCready playing with the camera. 2. MacCready family members and friends in back yard. 3. Waiting for the flyover of the B-2 Stealth plane before the Rose parade; floats. 4. MacCready with Taras Kiceniuk on electric bike 5. Paul MacCready using technalegs. 6. Black Sheep Squadron.
    - Main recording of Lambie Memorial, 1999 July 24; MacCreadyPB_07_03_021_14; Hi-8. Color. 30 min. (approx) (Box 7.21, Folder 14)
      Various people sharing their memories of Jack Lambie (friend of MacCready).
    - Lambie Memorial, 1999 July 24; MacCreadyPB_07_03_021_15; Hi-8. Runtime unknown (Box 7.21, Folder 15)
    - Sailplane Homebuilders Association meeting part 1, 1999 September 5; MacCreadyPB_07_03_021_16; Hi-8. Color. 20 min. (approx) (Box 7.21, Folder 16)
      Various presentations on overhead projector. Paul MacCready is operating camera.
    - Sailplane Homebuilders Association meeting part 2, 1999 September 5; MacCreadyPB_07_03_021_17; Hi-8. Color. 10 min. (approx) (Box 7.21, Folder 17)
      Various presentations on overhead projector.
    - El Mirage photo session/AO Dryden show/Helios/Proteus, 1999 October 13; MacCreadyPB_07_03_022_01; Hi-8. Color. 15 min. (approx) (Box 7.22, Folder 1)
      Footage of NASA press event in Mojave for Helios.
    - Tyler 4-legged crawler, Blacksheep Squadron, 1999 October 16 - June 2000; MacCreadyPB_07_03_022_02; Hi-8. Color. 40 min. (approx) (Box 7.22, Folder 2)
      1. Paul MacCready testing camera in his house for ~ 1 minute. 2.Tyler MacCready demonsrates his 4 legged robot for ~ 5 minutes. 3. Black Sheep Squadron meet at Luther Burbank School gym. Several members of AV are present ~ 6 minutes. 4. Paul, Judy and Marshall MacCready on boat ~ 2 minutes. 5. High school students showing bi-pedal walking robot demonstration. 6. Paul & others are in a rare book library ~ 2 minutes. 7. Men's rowing tournament at Marina del Rey (Marshall was one of the contestants) ~ 15 minutes.
    - Institute for Educational Advancement workshop with Black Sheep Squadron Model Airplane Club, 2000 July; MacCreadyPB_07_03_022_03; Hi-8. Color. 41 min. (Box 7.22, Folder 3)
      Unedited footage from kid's model airplane workshop. Paul MacCready is operating camera.
    - Homer and Hell Creek Tyrannosaurus [?], 2000 August; MacCreadyPB_07_03_022_04; Hi-8. Color. 30 min. (approx) (Box 7.22, Folder 4)
      Paul MacCready accompanies paleontologist Jack Horner (not in video) and group on a dig for tyrannosaurus bones. MacCready operates camera and asks people questions about what they are doing.
    - Fogel book release party, 2000 August; MacCreadyPB_07_03_022_05; Hi-8. Color. 10 min. (approx) (Box 7.22, Folder 5)
      Book release party for Gary Fogel. Paul MacCready is operating the camera talking to members of the party. One of the guests is Johnny Robinson - early glider pilot.
    - P-51 flights, M.O.F., 2000 September; MacCreadyPB_07_03_022_06; Hi-8. Color. 1 hour (approx) (Box 7.22, Folder 6)
      1. Paul MacCready recording friends in backyard [Bill Wyland?], looking at the art; recording friends at airport hangar; flying P-51. Tyler MacCready is featured as well. 2. Footage of fundraiser and hang gliders on Dockweiler Beach.
    - SHA (Sailplane Homebuilders Association). UAV tests. Part 1 of 2, 2000 September; MacCreadyPB_07_03_022_07; Hi-8. Color. 1 hour 15 min. (approx) (Box 7.22, Folder 7)
      1. Slideshow presentations to SHA. 2. UAV tests (Snoopy?) with Paul and Tyler MacCready (silent for about 10 minutes, then with sound).
    - SHA (Sailplane Homebuilders Association). Part 2 of 2, 2000 September 3; MacCreadyPB_07_03_022_08; Hi-8. Color. 1 hour 35 min. (approx) (Box 7.22, Folder 8)
      Presentations at SHA meeting.
    - 5 minutes of Snoopy III tests, Oak Grove. 11 minutes of Rose Bowl fly by video. 11 minutes of Black Sheep Squadron, 2000 October 28; November 23; December 18; MacCreadyPB_07_03_022_09; Hi-8. color. 30 min. (approx) (Box 7.22, Folder 9)
      1. Paul and Tyler MacCready testing Snoopy. Some footage is from the plane's camera. 2. Black Sheep Squadron at Luther Burbank School gym.
    - VHS Tapes AeroVironoment
    - Paul MacCready Anti-Stall Rotating Tip (Edited Tests of Rotating Tip Model), 1980; MacCreadyPB_07_03_023_01; VHS. 18 min. 45 sec. (Box 7.23, Folder 1)
      Various tests. Features Paul MacCready, Ray Morgan, Grant Gassman
    - Edited Bionic Bat video for Ultralight show - dupe. Proposed 1 min short from 16mm, ca. 1983; MacCreadyPB_07_03_023_02; VHS. 6 min. 30 sec. (Box 7.23, Folder 2)
      Rough footage of testing of bionic bat
    - AeroVironment Pointer Demonstration to Maj Gen Franklin U.S.M.C., 1988; MacCreadyPB_07_03_023_03; VHS. 5 min. (Box 7.23, Folder 3)
      Demonstration of AV's remote controlled glider at Camp Pendleton Marince Corps Base.
    - AeroVironment marketing tape (Broomstick), 1990; MacCreadyPB_07_03_023_04; VHS 7 min. 15 sec. (Box 7.23, Folder 4)
      Rough footage used for marketing tape; not the finished product. 1. POC Development of high altitude platform prototype 2. Broomstick
    - AeroVironment Vehicle Projects 1977 - 1991, 1991 June; MacCreadyPB_07_03_023_05; VHS. 8 min. 32 sec. (Box 7.23, Folder 5)
      Highlights of AV's accomplishments and inventions
    - AV Solar Car Brainstorming led by Paul MacCready, 1991 October 23; MacCreadyPB_07_03_023_06; VHS. 1 hour 1 min. (Box 7.23, Folder 6)
      Talk of designing a vehicle for the 1993 World Solar Challenge in Australia. Static camera in office. Camera is pointed at PBM and the backs of people's heads.
    - Solar/Electric Multi-Day Endurance High Altitude Aircraft, 1993 June 24; MacCreadyPB_07_03_023_07; VHS. 5 min. 48 sec. (Box 7.23, Folder 7)
      Video explaining the Pathfinder for the DOE
    - AeroVironment Ted Presentation rough cut: Doing More With Much Less, 1994 February 9; MacCreadyPB_07_03_023_08; VHS. 6 min. 50 sec. (Box 7.23, Folder 8)
      Rough edit of AV presentation. There is missing footage throughout.
    - NASA ERAST Remotely Piloted Aircraft: Hawaiian Volcano Air Emission Study, 1998 April; MacCreadyPB_07_03_023_09; VHS. 5 min. 45 sec. (Box 7.23, Folder 9)
      Demonstration of the use of AV's Pointer to collect Hawaii's volcanic atmospheric samples for NASA's ERAST.
    - Mars Aircraft Technology Demonstrator: Functional Deployment - Red Rock Canyon, CA, 1999; MacCreadyPB_07_03_023_10; VHS. 2 min. 32 sec. (Box 7.23, Folder 10)
      Demonstration of parachute deployment and landing of remotely piloted airplane.
    - Reconaissance & Surveillance Missions using AeroVironment's Small Flying Systems, 1999 December; MacCreadyPB_07_03_023_11; VHS. 5 min. 30 sec. (Box 7.23, Folder 11)
      Demonstrations of various small flying systems for the military.
    - DDC 20th Anniversary Project Compilation 1980 - 2000, 2000 February 18; MacCreadyPB_07_03_023_12; VHS. 53 min. 59 sec. (Box 7.23, Folder 12)
      Extensive overview of the various AV projects that were developed including Gossamer Condor, Gossamer Albatross, Helios, etc. Last few minutes includes a montage of the various people who worked for AV's Design Development Center.
    - "Pioneers of Flight" AeroVironment's Revolutionary Air Vehicles 1977 - 2000, 2000 February 27; MacCreadyPB_07_03_024_01; VHS. 25 min. (Box 7.24, Folder 1)
      Features some of the various AV projects that were developed including Gossamer Condor, Gossamer Albatross, Helios.
    - Impulse. 4 brief tests, 2000 July; MacCreadyPB_07_03_024_02; VHS. 2 min. 40 sec. (Box 7.24, Folder 2)
      Camera tests of UAV
    - California City Impulse Hi Start, 2000 July 12; MacCreadyPB_07_03_024_03; VHS. 21 min. 30 sec. (Box 7.24, Folder 3)
      Tests of UAV camera.
    - Turkey Vultures/Simi 9:15 - 9:30 am, 2000 July 23; MacCreadyPB_07_03_024_04; VHS. 8 min. (Box 7.24, Folder 4)
      Personal video/home movie.
    - Black Widow MAV (Micro Air Vehicle) Summary: 30 Minute Flight Test, 2000 August; MacCreadyPB_07_03_024_05; VHS. 13 min. 50 sec. (Box 7.24, Folder 5)
      Camera footage from the MAV looking down at AV offices.
    - Tests, 2000 August; MacCreadyPB_07_03_024_06; VHS. 28 min. (Box 7.24, Folder 6)
    - Antenna tests, 2000 September 1; MacCreadyPB_07_03_024_07; VHS. 2 hours 4 min. (Box 7.24, Folder 7)
      Tests of UAV camera/antenna. Location unknown.
    - Fuel Cells & Helios Prototype on CNN, KCOP - 13, KABC - 7, KCAL - 9., 2000 October 29 - 30; MacCreadyPB_07_03_024_08; VHS. 7 min. (Box 7.24, Folder 8)
      NASA/Solar energy press release. Almost identical footage used on all 4 segments. Features clip of Tom Convers of Aero Vironment and footage of Marshall MacCready.
    - Pointer Demo to Col. Regan Springs USAF Force Protection Battlelab, Lackland, AFB, 2000 November; MacCreadyPB_07_03_024_09; VHS. 8 min. (Box 7.24, Folder 9)
    - Doing More with Much Less, 2001; MacCreadyPB_07_03_024_10; VHS. 6 min. 50 sec. (Box 7.24, Folder 10)
      What can be done with low power. Pathfinder, GA, Goldrush, Flying Fish, Sunraycer, Impact, Electric Assist on bike, AV Pointer, Sailplanes, Solar Challenger.
    - MicroBat 2 - Minute Flight, 2001; MacCreadyPB_07_03_024_11; VHS. 5 min. 40 sec. (Box 7.24, Folder 11)
      Endurance test of the MicroBat prototype.
    - Helios Prototype HP-01, 2001; MacCreadyPB_07_03_024_12; VHS. 9 min. (Box 7.24, Folder 12)
    - DDC Bloopers 1980 - 2000, 2001; MacCreadyPB_07_03_024_13; VHS. 27 min. (Box 7.24, Folder 13)
    - Small UAV (Unmanned Aerial Vehicles) Video, 2002 July; MacCreadyPB_07_03_024_14; VHS. 15 min. (Box 7.24, Folder 14)
      Short demo reel of: GLUAV(Gun Launched UAV) for US Army, Dragon Eye for US Marines, X-Glider (Expendable Gliding Delivery System) for US Navy, X-UAV-TP (Expendable Turbine Powered UAV) for DOD-OSD, X-UAV-GL (Ependable Glider UAV) for DOD-OSD, X-UAV-EP (Expendable Electric Powered UAV) for DOD-OSD, Pointer UAV for Dismounted Light Forces for US Army, Raven UAV for Dismounted Light Forces for US Army, OAV(Organic Air Vehicle) for DARPA, Black Widow Micro Air Vehicle for DARPA, Hoverfly Micro Scale Research Aircraft for DARPA, MicroBat Micro Air Vehicle for DARPA.
    - Untitled (AV employees), MacCreadyPB_07_03_024_15; Hi-8. 7 min. 30 sec. (Box 7.24, Folder 15)
    - Cassette tapes
      Oversized
    - Portion of CBC radio program on MacCready Gossamer Condor, 1977 August 5; MacCreadyPB_07_03_025_01; audio cassette (Box 7.25, Folder 1)
    - MacCready - Gossamer Condor. AIAA, 1977 Fall; MacCreadyPB_07_03_025_02; 2 audio cassettes (Box 7.25, Folder 2)
    - The Gossamer Condor, Dr. Paul MacCready. Ramo Auditorium, Caltech, 1977 October 3; MacCreadyPB_07_03_025_03; audio cassette (Box 7.25, Folder 3)
    - Gossamer Condor. KFWB (partial recording), 1977 October 5; MacCreadyPB_07_03_025_04; audio cassette (Box 7.25, Folder 4)
    - GC installation at NASM, news report of flight, 1978 March 3; MacCreadyPB_07_03_025_05; audio cassette (Box 7.25, Folder 5)
    - MPA group at Marston, 1979 June 23; MacCreadyPB_07_03_025_06; audio cassette (Box 7.25, Folder 6)
    - Tape SSA-1048. Aerodynamics of low powered vehicles: Paul MacCready. SSA National Convention, 1989; MacCreadyPB_07_03_025_07; audio cassette (Box 7.25, Folder 7)
    - Gell-Mann, Lindbergh Fund, 1993 May 26; MacCreadyPB_07_03_025_08; 2 audio cassettes (Box 7.25, Folder 8)
  - Film, 4
    - LARP (Low Altitude Retriever Probe), ca. 1950s; MacCreadyPB_07_04_026_01; 16mm. Color. 5 min. (approx) (Box 7.26, Folder 1)
      Created by MRI. Footage of men flying LARP planes in grassy area.
    - HARP (High Altitude Retriever Probe), ca. 1950s; MacCreadyPB_07_04_027_01; 16mm. Color. 5 min. (approx) (Box 7.27, Folder 1)
      Created by MRI. Footage of Paul MacCready et al. testing HARP, balloons, etc.
    - Miscellaneous Gossamer Condor scenes, 1977; MacCreadyPB_07_04_028_01; 16mm. Color. 6 min. (Box 7.28, Folder 1)
      Created byJoe Mastropaolo. Footage of the Gossamer Condor.
    - Pumping Mylar, 1977; MacCreadyPB_07_04_029_01; 16mm. Color. 3 min. (Box 7.29, Folder 1)
      Created by Bill Rickson. Footage of Bryan Allen flying Gossamer Condor.
    - Gossamer Condor Kremer flight, 1977 August 23; MacCreadyPB_07_04_030_01; 16mm. Color. 10 min. (approx) (Box 7.30, Folder 1)
      Created by Centre Films. Footage of Bryan Allen et al.
    - Gossamer Condor Kremer flight footage, 1977 August 23; MacCreadyPB_07_04_031_01; 16mm. Color. 3 min. (approx) (Box 7.31, Folder 1)
      [Possibly created by Centre Films]. Outtakes of the Kremer flight
    - Gossamer Condor, 1977 August 23; MacCreadyPB_07_04_032_01; 16mm. Color. 3 min. 10 sec. (Box 7.32, Folder 1)
      Footage of Bryan Allen flying Gossamer Condor at Shafter airport for Kremer prize
    - Misc. Gossamer Condor flight footage, 1977 November 12; MacCreadyPB_07_04_033_01; 16mm. Color. 10 min. (approx) (Box 7.33, Folder 1)
      Crated by: Carl Battjes. Taken after the Kremer flight